Finding aid to the Carole A. Oglesby papers SSC.MS.00492
Sophia Smith Collection
Carole A. Oglesby papers
1950-2018
Sophia Smith Collection
Oglesby, Carole A.
SSC.MS.00492
79.501 linear feet (95 boxes)
88 items (23 external USB drives, 12 CDs, 27 3.5 floppy disks, 9 DVDs, 17 VHS tapes)
Carole A. Oglesby is a pioneer in the women's sports movement and one of the first "out" lesbians in U.S. athletics. The bulk of this collection represents Oglesby's professional activities, research and extensive writings, and contains materials related to women and sport in the United States and worldwide beginning in the 1950's.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Carole A. Oglesby in multiple groupings in 2003 and 2018.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into series based on when the materials were sent to the archive by Oglesby. The first series contains the accession that was sent in 2003 and all other series were received in 2018.
Biographical Note
Carole A. Oglesby is one of the pioneers in the women's sports movement beginning and one of the first "out" lesbians in U.S. athletics.
Oglesby earned her A.B. and her M.S. in physical education at the University of California, Los Angeles, in 1961 and 1964 respectively; in 1969 she received her Ph.D. from Purdue University. She served as the first president of the Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (AIAW), and as the first president of Women Sport International. Oglesby opposed the merger of the AIAW with the National Collegiate Athletic Association in 1982.
A leader in numerous national organizations, she has served as president of the National Association for Girls and Women in Sport(NAGWS), and as trustee for the Women's Sports Foundation (WSF). She organized WSF's "The New Agenda" conference, which set the research agenda for women in sport in the early 1980s, including homophobia in sport. She also served on the executive committee of the United States Collegiate Sports Council for twenty-five years, an arm of the International Federation of University Sport, which organizes the World University Games.
Oglesby wrote extensively. In addition to her book, Women in Sport: From Myth to Reality, she was the editor of the Encyclopedia of Women in Sport in America, as well as several other monographs. She authored hundreds of articles, editorial columns, book chapters, and book reviews and has also been the editor of several journals relating to education, sport, sex roles, and psychology.
In addition to her work nationally, Oglesby has travelled the globe, explicating the connection between women's sports and women's rights, and she serves as a consultant to many athletic and women's groups. After nearly forty years of teaching at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst, Purdue University, and Temple University, Oglesby went back to school to earn a Ph.D. in Counseling Psychology at Temple University. She is certified as a trained practitioner in Eye Movement Desensitization Reprocessing (EMDR), and taught at California State University, Northridge, where she headed the Department of Kinesiology. She currently serves as the International Policy and Program Advisor for the Women's Sports Foundation(WSF).
Organizations documented in the collection (alphabetized by initialisms; bolded indicate some of the orgs where she held office or had a significant relationship in)
AAASP - Association for the Advancement of Applied Sports Psychology
AAC - Association of American Colleges
AAPERD - American Alliance for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance
AALR - American Association for Leisure and Recreation
AAU - Amateur Athletic Union
AAUP - American Association of University Professors
ABA - Amatuer Basketball Association
ABLA - Amateur Bicycle League of America
AHSA - American Horse Shows Association
AIAW - Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women
ACIS - American Council on International Sports
ACTI - Athletic Counseling & Treatment Institute
AMA - American Motorcycle Association
ASA - Amateur Softball Association
ASCA - American Swimming Coaches Association
ASUUS - Amateur Skating Union of the United States
AWPENYS - Association of Women in Physical Education of New York State
CESU - Commission pour l'etude du Sport Universitaire
CNCA - Council for National Cooperation in Aquatics
FISU - International University Sports Federation
IAAF - International Association of Athletics Federations
IAPESGW - International Association of Physical Education and Sports for Girls and Women
ICHPER - International Council for Health, Physical Education and Recreation
IOC - International Olympic Committee
IWG - International Working Group on Women and Sport
MAPECW - Midwestern Association of Physical Education for College women
NACWAA - National Association of Collegiate Women Athletic Administrators
NAGWS - National Association for Girls and Women in Sports
NAIA - National Association for Intercollegiate Athletics
NANWR
NASPE - National Association for Sport and Physical Education (its Sports Psychology Academy started 1975)
NASPSA - North American Society for the Psychology of Sport and Physical Activity
NASSS - North American Society for the Sociology of Sport
NCAA - National Collegiate Athletic Association
NISC - National Intramural Sports Council
NJCAA - National Junior College Athletic Association
NOW - National Organization for Women
NRA - National Rifle Association of America
NWRA - National Womens Rowing Association
PCPFS - President's Council on Physical Fitness and Sports
USBF - United States Baseball Federation
USTCA - United States Track Coaches Association
USCSC - United States Collegiate Sports Council
USFSA - United States Figure Skating Association
USGF - United States Gymnastics Federation
USJF - United States Judo Federation
USOC - United States Olympic Committee
USMPBA - United States Modern Pentathon and Biathlon Association
USPA - United States Parachute Association
USSF - United States Soccer Federation
USTFF - United States Track and Field Association
USVA - United States Volleyball Association
USYRU - United States Yacht Racing Union
WAA - Women's Action Alliance
WAGC - World Amateur Golf Council
WEAL - Women's Equality Action League
WIBC - Women's International Bowling Congress
WLRA - World Leisure and Recreation Association
WSF - Women's Sports Foundation
WSI - WomenSport International
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
Separated Materials
A few books not authored by Oglesby in the collection were found to be moldy and discarded at the time of accessioning, as was an original copy of Oglesby's thesis, a photocopy of which was retained. Confidential student and records of other's containing Social Security numbers, grades, medical or other personal information have been removed.
In 2019 several groups of materials were removed fromt the 2003 accession, including: unrelated books, pamphlets, newsletters, songbooks, and catalogs; widely available music; blank stationary and duplicate materials; unrelated objects and memorabilia; and one folder of material related to several children in South America that Oglesby sponsored through school. One folder related to Chris Shelton was moved to the Chris Shelton papers.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of this collection represents Carole Oglesby's professional activities, research and extensive writings. It contains materials related to the women and sport from the 1950s to the early 2000s.
Subtopics include homophobia in sport, racial awareness in women's sport, Title IX, the relationship between women's sport and feminism, and international women's conferences. Organizations represented in the collection include the American Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance; National Association for Girls and Women in Sport; United States Olympic Committee; United States Collegiate Sports Council; International Federation of University Sport (IFUS); American Association for Applied Sports Psychology; Commission on the Status of Women; and the Women's Sports Foundation. Projects and conferences in the collection include the New Agenda, a conference planning the future of research in women's sport; the COACH project, which worked with Pennsylvania high school coaches; the 1977 Torch Run to Houston; and International Women's Year.
Oglesby's correspondence covers a wide range of personal, political and professional subjects, and reflects her role as a mentor and advocate for both students and professional colleagues. Additionally, there are letters to editors and others that reflect her advocacy for her own writing and reputation, especially when editors used her work without giving her credit. Her correspondence with other women who were instrumental in women and sport reveals a close personal network. A single letter or email might contain both discussion of their personal lives and relationships as well as discussions of current professional work that was going on in women's sport organizations and networks. Some correspondence and other materials are related to Oglesby's former partner, Christine Shelton, professor emerita of Exercise and Sport Studies at Smith College.
The collection also contains a small amount administrative files and teaching materials from Temple University and the University of Massachusetts at Amherst. This includes documentation of her leadership in the American Association of University Professors during the faculty strike at Temple.
African American women athletes--History--20th century--Sources; Lesbian athletes--History--20th century--Sources; Homophobia in sports--History--20th century--Sources; Physical education for women--History--20th century--Sources; Physical education teachers--History--20th century--Sources; Sports for women--History--20th century--Sources; Oglesby, Carol A.; American Association for Health, Physical Education, and Recreation. Division for Girls and Women's Sports--History--Sources; American Association of University Professors--History--Sources; Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women--History--Sources; International Women's Year, 1975; National Association for Girls and Women in Sport--History--Sources; Temple University--Faculty--History--Sources; United Nations Commission on the Status of Women--History--Source; Women's Sports Foundation--History--Sources; Women and Sport, Title IX, United States Collegiate Sports Council, AAASP, Commission on the Status of Women, The New Agenda, COACH project, 1977 Torch Run; Shelton, Christine; Agendas; Appointment books; Audiotapes; Awards; Bibliographies; Books; Brochures; Business cards; Buttons (information artifacts); Bylaws; clippings; correspondence; Electronic mail; Faxes; Financial records; Interviews; Invoices; lecture notes; Manuscripts; memorabilia; Minutes; Memorandums; Newsletters; newspaper clippings; Research; Pamphlets; Periodicals; photographs; press releases; reports; Resolutions; Sheet music; Speeches; Theses; Writings; CDs; Videotapes; DVD video discs; Oglesby, Carole A.; Oglesby, Carole A.
- Carole A. Oglesby papers, 1964-2003; Accession 2003-S-0070; 51.417 linear feet (60 containers)
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials donated by Carole Oglesby in 2003. The bulk of these materials related to women and sports from the 1960s to the early 2000s.
  Subtopics include homophobia in sport, racial awareness in women's sport, Title IX, the relationship between women's sport and feminism, sports psychology and international women's conferences.
  The papers in this series reflect Oglesby's involvement and leadership role in dozens of organizations, including the American Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance; National Association for Girls and Women in Sport; United States Olympic Committee; United States Collegiate Sports Council; International Federation of University Sport (IFUS); American Association for Applied Sports Psychology; Commission on the Status of Women; and the Women's Sports Foundation. A full list is included in the collection level History and Biography note.
  Projects and conferences documented here include the New Agenda, a conference held to plan the future of research in women's sport; the COACH project, which worked with Pennsylvania high school coaches; the 1977 Torch Run to Houston; and International Women's Year.
  Other materials include administrative files of Temple University and the University of Massachusetts at Amherst, including materials from Oglesby's activism in the Association of American University Professors (AAUP) keading up to and during a faculty strike. Correspondence in this series includes letters and emails with family members and her professional cohort in America and across the world. Letters and emails reflect close friendships with women leaders in women sport organizations who were working together to navigate a profession dominated by men and make space for women athletes, coaches and teachers. The ovwrlap of personal and professional in their correspondence exemplify a slogan of the larger Women's Movement, "The personal is political." There is some correspondence and other papers related to Christine Shelton, her former partner and a Smith College professor emeritus.
  Also included are documents related to Oglesby's extensive writings, which include books, journal and magazine articles and opinion pieces.
  Separated Materials
  In 2019, approximately 10 record boxes of materials were removed from the collection. These included: unrelated books, pamphlets, newsletters, songbooks, and catalogs; student grades; widely available music; blank stationary and duplicate materials; unrelated objects and memorabilia; and one folder of material related to several children in South America that Oglesby sponsored through school. One folder related to Chris Shelton was moved to the Chris Shelton papers.
  - Personal: Birthday, holiday, and other personal cards (Box 1)
  - Personal: Correspondence, 1967-2003 (Box 1)
  - Personal: Local Philadelphia events and organizations (Box 1)
  - Personal: Travel (Box 1)
  - Personal: Education and coursework: General (Box 1)
  - Personal: Education and coursework: Purdue (Box 1)
  - Personal: Reflections (Box 2)
  - Personal: Clippings and collected publications (Box 2)
  - Personal: Music and poetry (Box 2)
  - Personal: Hospital visit (Box 2)
  - Personal: House (Box 2)
  - Personal: Calendars and diaries (Box 2)
  - Personal: Scrapbooks and albums (Box 2, Box 3)
  - Professional: Coaching (Box 3)
  - Professional: Vita material (Box 3)
  - Professional: Teaching, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
  - Professional: Applications to faculty positions and gen. personnel files (Box 3)
  - Professional: Educational testing services (Box 3)
  - Professional: Correspondence: Recommendations (Box 3)
  - Professional: Correspondence, 1970-2003 (Box 3)
  - Professional: Faculty position announcements (Box 3)
  - Professional: Project FATE (Box 3)
  - Professional: Project TEAM (Box 3)
  - Professional: Image Quest (Box 3)
  - Professional: Image Quest: Fitness Leaders Manual (Box 4)
  - Professional: Consulting: General (Box 4)
  - Professional: Consulting: Swarthmore (Box 4)
  - Professional: Consulting: Slippery Rock (Box 4)
  - Professional: Workshops on sexual harassment and sexual ethics in athletics, 1990-1998 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Elizabeth (Libby) Darlinson, 1995-2000 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Anita Diamont, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Julie Dykema (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Billie Jean King (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Jeanette Madrick (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Maria Nelson (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Adrienne Rich, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Emails (Temple account) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Email mailing list, "Amazon International", 1992 (Box 6)
  - Awards and recognition (Box 7)
  - Questionnaires and surveys (Box 7)
  - Clippings (Box 7)
  - Notes (Box 8)
  - Research: Studies, articles (Box 8)
  - Research: Journal and other papers (Box 8)
  - Research (Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12)
    - King material in cutting sports (Box 8)
    - Articles on women and sports (Box 10)
  - Organizations: U.S. Olympic Committee (Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19)
  - World University Games (Box 19, Box 20, Box 21)
  - Organizations: United States Collegiate Sports Council (Box 20)
  - International Organizations: General (Box 21)
  - International Organizations: Africa (Box 21)
  - International Organizations: Australia/New Zealand (Box 21)
  - International Organizations: South and Central America (Box 21)
  - International Organizations: Canada (Box 21)
  - International Organizations: Europe (Box 22)
  - International Organizations: Japan (Box 22)
  - International Organizations: Middle East (Box 22)
  - International Organizations: USSR/Russia (Box 22)
  - International Council for Health, Physical Education, and Recreation (ICHPER) (Box 22)
  - International Working Group on Women and Sport (IWG) (Box 22, Box 23)
  - Pan American Congress on Physical Education (Box 23)
  - Interamerican Congress on Sports and Recreation for Girls and Women (Box 23)
  - Pan American Games (Box 23)
  - WomenSport International (Box 23)
  - Organization of American States (Box 23)
  - European Women and Sport (EWS) (Box 23)
  - Central Council of Physical Recreation (Box 23)
  - 11th Congress of International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women (IAPESGW) (Box 23)
  - International Society of Sport Psychology (ISSP) symposium (Box 23)
  - National Women's Conference (Box 24)
  - United Nations Decade for Women (Box 24)
  - United Nations International Women's Year (Box 24)
  - International Women's Year Conference on Sport planning meeting (Box 24)
  - United Nations Empower the Girl Child working group correspondence (Box 24)
  - United Nations Achieve Educational Equality working group correspondence (Box 24)
  - United Nations Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women (CEDAW) (Box 24)
  - United Nations Commission on the Status of Women (CSW) (Box 24)
  - United Nations NGO forums (Box 24)
  - United Nations/UNESCO general (Box 24, Box 25)
  - Organizations: general (Box 25)
  - Women's Equity Action League (WEAL) (Box 25)
  - American Psychological Association (APA) (Box 25)
  - National Association for Sports and Physical Education (NASPE) (Box 25)
  - Amateur Athletic Association (AAU) (Box 25)
  - Women's Agenda of Pennsylvania (Box 25)
  - American Association of University Women (AAUW) (Box 25)
  - National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) (Box 25)
  - National Association for Physical Education in Higher Education (NAPEHE) (Box 25)
  - Amateur Basketball Association of the USA (ABA USA) (Box 25)
  - Girls' Coalition of Southern Pennsylvania, 1988-1990 (Box 25)
  - National Organization of Women (NOW), 1978 (Box 25)
  - Girls Clubs of America, 1985-1995 (Box 25)
  - Project on the Status and Education of Women, Association of American Colleges, 1978-1980 (Box 25)
  - Celebrate Women (Box 25)
  - Sports Psychology Academy (Box 26)
  - Women's Action Alliance, Inc. (Box 26)
  - National Coalition for Sex Equality in Education (NCSEE) (Box 26)
  - National Ski Area Association (NSAA) (Box 26)
  - Melpomene Institute (Box 26)
  - North American Society for Psychology of Sport and Physical Activity (NASPSPA) (Box 26)
  - National Association for Girls and Women in Sport (NAGWS) (Box 26, Box 27, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30)
  - Women's Sports Foundation (WSF) (Box 30, Box 31, Box 32, Box 33)
  - American Alliance for Health, Physical Education, Recreation, and Dance (AAHPERD) (Box 34, Box 35, Box 36)
  - Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (AIAW) (Box 36, Box 37, Box 38)
  - Association for the Advancement of Applied Sports Psychology (AAASP) (Box 38, Box 39)
  - People to People Citizen Ambassador Program (Box 39)
  - People to People Citizen Ambassador Program: Women in Sports Delegation to Russia and Belarus, 1992-1994 (Box 39)
  - People to People Citizen Ambassador Program: Women in Sports Delegation to China, 1993-1994 (Box 40)
  - Philadelphia School District (Box 40)
  - National Women's Conference (Box 40)
  - Temple University: Departments (Box 41, Box 42)
  - Temple University: Teaching (Box 42, Box 43, Box 44, Box 45)
  - Course work: other universities (Box 45)
  - Temple University: Correspondence (Box 45)
  - Temple University: General (Box 45)
  - Faculty Newspaper: Temple Herald (Box 45)
  - Temple University: American Association of University Professors (AAUP) (Box 45, Box 46, Box 47)
  - Conferences and events (Box 47)
  - Speeches and presentations (Box 47, Box 48)
  - Writings: Women and Sport: From Myth to Reality (Box 48)
  - Writings: Correspondence (Box 48)
  - Writings: Basic Stuff series, Psychosocial Aspects, June 5, 1985 - October 23, 1986 (Box 48)
  - Writings: Journal articles (Box 48)
  - Writings: Papers (Box 48)
  - Writings: Reviews of peer texts (Box 48)
  - Writings: Chapters, essays in books (Box 48)
  - Writings: Project did not materialize (Box 49)
  - Writings: "The Role of Girls and Women in Developing Physical Education and Sport Programs" (Box 49)
  - Writings: Op Eds/ Letters to the Editor (Box 49)
  - Writings: Unidentified (Box 49)
  - Writings: Miscellaneous bibliographies (Box 49)
  - Writings: Encyclopedia of Women and Sport in America (Box 49)
  - Writings: Sports and Moral Identity in Lesbians (Box 50)
  - Writings: Encyclopedia of Women and Sport in America research, notes, manuscripts, 1996-1998 (Box 50)
  - SUBJECT FILES: LGBT (Box 50, Box 51)
  - SUBJECT FILES: Title IX lawsuit and other general materials (Box 52, Box 53)
  - SUBJECT FILES: Women of colors in sports (Box 52)
  - SUBJECT FILES: Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) (Box 52)
  - SUBJECT FILES: Youth sports (Box 52)
  - SUBJECT FILES: Press, film proposal and general media (Box 52)
  - SUBJECT FILES: Sports psychology, kinesiology, and EMDR materials (Box 52, Box 53)
  - SUBJECT FILES: equity and gender in sport general materials (Box 53)
  - PUBLICATIONS: Women and Sport (Box 53, Box 54)
  - PUBLICATIONS: various women newsletters, journals, articles and other publications regarding softball and women sports, 1971-1987 (Box 54)
  - PUBLICATIONS: sports psychology magazines, newsletters and journals, 1973-2003 (Box 54)
  - PUBLICATIONS: Book, Repeat After Me by Claudia Black, 1987 (Box 54)
  - PUBLICATIONS: Book, Coaching Girls and Women by Pasty E. Neal and Thomas H. Tutko, 1975 (Box 54)
  - Miscellaneous books by other authors, 1975-2000 (Box 55)
  - PUBLICATIONS: Miscellaneous journals, magazines and articles on feminism and politics (Box 55, Box 56)
  - Research materials on various aspects of women and sports (Box 56)
  - Conference and event pins, name badges, ribbons; All-American Girls Professional Baseball League card set and other memorabilia (Box 57)
  - Unidentified film, 6 Reels Film, 8mm (Box 58)
    Four unlabelled, all from 1964. One is labelled "Wheeling + Oglebay 1965" and one is labelled "1 Vac 1965." Three moldy tapes were separated, two unlabelled, one labelled "2 Vac 1965"
  - Unidentified open reel audiotape, 3 Reels Audiotape open reel, 1/4 inch. One reel is 3 inch diameter, one 5 inch, and one 7 inch. (Box 58)
  - Slides of Winter World University Games, Lake Placid, 1972; 37 Photographic Slides (Box 58)
  - Jan Interview, 1 Cassettes Audio cassette (Box 58)
  - Pam Mendy Interview, 1 Cassettes Audio cassette (Box 58)